There are a few different ways to manage
positions and look after your trades
when you're already in them. One of them
is stop-loss trading, and that is what
we're going to talk about today. I'm
going to show you what stop-loss trading
is and how you can use it correctly to
create win-win scenarios in your
trading, which ultimately will help you
to increase your total profits. So,
let's get straight to it. So, what
exactly is stop-loss trailing then?
Well, when you get into a trade, you
should set a stop-loss order on every
trade. So, for this, this is our entry.
This is our target, and this is our
stop-loss. Now, your stop-loss is going
to get you out of a trade if a trade
goes bad. But the bonus of stop- losses
is once we place them, we don't have to
leave them exactly where they are. We
can actually move the stop-loss order
different ways to different prices. Now,
we should never extend a stop-loss
because if we get into a trade risking,
for example, $1,000 on this stop loss,
if we double the size of that stop loss,
we're actually now risking $2,000. So,
it's impossible to manage risk if you
extend your stop loss that way. But what
we can actually do is grab our stop-loss
order. So, let's say this is indicating
the stop-loss and we can pull it in to
the entry price, for example. Now, if we
pulled the stop loss to the entry price
and the market went up a little bit but
then reversed on us, rather than taking
a loss, if the market got down here, we
would actually be closed out of the
trade at this point, which means rather
than losing money, we would just be out
of the trade for break even. Okay? Which
means we do not take a loss and means
essentially we've won this position in a
sense that it didn't cost us money. Now,
we can also move our stop-loss into
profit. Obviously, we can't do this if
the market price is under where we would
like to put the stop- loss. But if a
trade starts to move in our favor, we
can actually utilize this ability to
move stop- losses by doing what we call
trailing. So, let's say this position
moves in our favor up to this point and
then we start to create some new
structure. What we could do in this
instance would be move our stop loss up
to follow the structure. So this way, if
the market pulls back, finds a new low,
and continues the trend, we can simply
trail again. But if the market is to
make a full-blown reversal and move all
the way down here, rather than getting
stopped out for a loss, which is not
good, or break even and missing out on
all of the profit potential we have in
this area, we would actually be stopped
out of our trade at this level here.
Now, if we think about what that would
do for us, well, our 5.5% potential
trade would be stopped out here at
1.8%. Of course, we didn't get the full
5.5% that we wanted, but we've still
taken a positive outcome on this trade.
Okay? Rather than making $0 or making
minus 1%, we've actually made plus 1.8
because we trailed the stop. So
stop-loss trading is simply utilizing
the fact that we can move stop-loss
orders and following price with our
stop-loss as the market moves up. If we
do this, we can actually minimize the
possibility of this trade turning into a
0% trade or a losing trade and we can
maximize the profits that a trade can
provide us because we can actually close
it as soon as it starts flipping on us.
Now, there is a right way and there is a
wrong way to trail your stop. If the
market is moving up in your favor, what
you shouldn't do is just run your stop
up immediately behind price. Okay? So,
let's say price moved from here to here.
You don't want to just follow it
directly with your stop because as we
know, markets rarely ever move perfectly
upwards or perfectly downwards. Most of
the time, if we look at smaller price
action or smaller charts, we're going to
have some movements like this going on,
right? which is of course likely to lead
us to being stopped out by market noise
on the way up towards the target. So
because markets are prone to moving up
and down and we could get movements like
this before the target is hit, it's
important that we're smart with our
trailing. The best way to trail stops to
avoid the problems we've just discussed
is to follow structure. Okay, so
structure refers to highs and lows in a
market. Now if we take a look at this
market example here, let's say we have
our stop loss in its initial position.
We can mark structure up from high and
low perspective. So this is our high.
Here we have a low. Here we have a lower
high. And here we have a lower low. We
have a lower high. And then we have the
low, the lowest point. Okay. So this
phase of price action based on structure
is bearish. That's a market that's
moving down. In this instance, we would
want to sell. The formation of the trade
that we got happened after we had a
break of structure here. So a break of
structure is simply a point of which the
structure breaks. The previous low,
previous high breaks and gives way to
new price action. So this would be our
break of structure on the downside as
would this and as would this where we're
seeing the market price breaking
consistently into new lows. Now I see
this here as a break of structure into a
new high. This is the start of an
uptrend. You might know this as a change
of character. For me, that's kind of
pointless terminology. I don't use it,
but that may be what you've heard of
that if you've traded price action
before, uh, and you're confused as to
why I call that a break of structure.
Now, the market at this point is
trending up. How do we know that? Here
we have a high, then we create a higher
low. So, this low is higher than the
previous one. Then we create a higher
high, a higher low, higher high, higher
low, and so on and so on. You get the
idea, right? So, what we're actually
doing is looking at the real highs and
lows inside of the price structure. And
this is how we're formulating ideas as
to which way the market's going. Now,
how is this relevant to stop-loss
trading? Well, that is because we are
going to follow the highs and lows in
price to actually decide where to put
our stop loss. With this initial move up
here, we're not going to do anything
with this stop at this point because
there's every possibility that after
pushing up, the market pulls back down
and then continues after making a new
high just above this previous one. So,
because of that, we don't really want to
move the stop based off of the first
price movement. Then we see this point
here, the market pulls back, creates a
new low, and then pushes up and creates
a new high. So this high here validates
the structure. Right? At this point we
have had a movement up a validated low
and a new validated high. The high and
the low is validated when we get the
break of structure. Our breakup
structure in this instance took place at
this level here. The point where this
high was broken by price creating this
new high which validates this higher
low. At this point, we could actually
trail the stop to under this structural
low here. The reason we can do that is
because if the market is then to reverse
and take out this low, we could be
seeing here a change in the trending
structure of the market. We've actually
then gone from a market phase of upward
higher highs and higher lows and we
would be shifting back into a new lower
low with a break of structure under the
current price action of the uptrend.
This is then likely to be followed by a
pullback and sell which would generally
lead us to losing or breaking even on
the position. So basically what we're
doing here is waiting for validation of
a trend in this format that we've just
discussed. Then we can follow price by
putting the stop loss under the recently
formed higher low. As you can see then
after creating this high the market
pulls back and creates a new higher low.
This higher low is not validated until
we create this high. When the market
creates a break of structure over the
previous high just here, the breaker
structure being here. This closure up
here validates the initial low. The low
being this one in this example. So at
this point, we could then safely trail
the stop loss from here under this
structural low to here under this
structural low because we know that the
higher highs and higher lows of the
market continuing up and up and up and
with the formation of this high, we've
validated the formation of this low and
the market shouldn't really move under
this low if it's continuing in its
uptrend. All right. Once again, then we
come down, we form a low here. This low
is validated when there is a break of
structure here creating this new high.
So we can actually pull the stop up to
this level and trail it under this low.
Now if the market had then created a
high, validated the high and we trailed
the stop and then decided to reverse on
us. So if we'd have had a movement down
like this, we'd be stopped out here
instead of all the way down back at our
entry or at our stop loss. This means we
would have created a profitable trade
here of 2.2%. 2% which obviously yes is
not the full percentage target we want
but it is still a lot better than the
trade going all the way back to zero or
to negative. So that's the idea behind
stop-loss trading. Structure is the one
big thing we want to look at. And now
let's go over to a chart and I'll show
you how this looks in action. All right.
So in this example we are going to look
at a trade on GBP AUD which is a selling
opportunity. So it works the exact same
way for sells except you are going to
trail your stop loss over highs as the
market structure breaks down. The
position is just now executed. Our
initial stop-loss order to get us out of
a trade in a loss scenario is above this
high. For now we don't want to move it.
We need to see some structure form
before we can actually consider moving
our stop loss. So we can look at the
recently printed low. We need to
remember though that until we close
underneath this level, there is no
validation of this low. Okay, the market
could realistically move higher. So, we
don't want to trail stopped until the
market's pushed under this low, allowing
the market to play forwards. We see we
get a nice downward move initially. At
this point, still no trailing would take
place. Now, one very important thing
about this trailing system is that you
need to stay time frame relative. That
means for example in this position we
executed here on the 30 minute time
frame. We don't really want to go lower
than the 30 minute to determine the
structure because as we discussed before
there is noise on lower time frames. If
we execute on the 30 minute and then we
go to the five minute, there is going to
be trends inside of trends taking place
right here where I've just drawn this
line. Which means we may be drawn in
induced to actually move our stop-loss
into profit or trail it at least behind
price based on 5minute price action when
realistically the market could chop back
and hit those stops. Okay? such as just
down here. We created this low, we
pulled back, and then we've pushed back
up. If we'd have trailed our stop loss
based on low time frame structure, we
might be out of this trade, even though
it still has all the room to move lower.
So, now that we've validated and closed
beneath this low, we can take the first
step to trailing our stop. And that's
going to be nice and simple. We are just
going to pull it to the entry level.
Okay, this is now what we call stop-loss
to break even. That would essentially
pull the stop loss all the way to the
entry point, meaning if the market
reverses on us, we will not take a loss.
We will be out for $0 profit, $0 loss.
Okay, I'm going to leave this to
visualize the riskreward, but we've
pulled the actual simulated trade
stop-loss down to the entry point. Now,
we are in a win or no loss scenario. We
can also go ahead at the moment and
start to look at the low that's just
been printed because if the market was
to pull up and validate a high by coming
back down and breaking through this low
that would give us what we need to
actually trail the stop down to this
point for example. So let's run it
forward and see what the market gets up
to here. Once again keeping it relevant
to the time frames. So we're going to be
working with the 30inut. Okay. So, as of
right now, basically, as we understand,
providing the market stays under this
high, it is still in a valid downtrend,
and we can happily hold the stop where
it is without worrying too much about
getting stopped out. And if we do get
stopped out, it's generally going to be
because the market is pushing up and
breaking structure, which would
invalidate our position. And at that
point, we'd rather be out risk-free.
Okay, so we're seeing the market pulling
down. And here, we've created a candle
closure. Our first break of structure
was here, which allowed us to trail the
stop to even. Our second break of
structure has just taken place here,
which would allow us to trail our stop
down under the next structural point.
That, for me, is going to be this wick
area. I'm going to pull this over so it
stops being annoying. We could pull the
stop to just above this level. It's not
too much further, but it gives us at
least a small win in the worst case
scenario if the market was to flip
against us. Now we would like to see for
continuation of this trend a new high
followed by a new low to validate the
high and then we could follow the market
down with our stop. So let's see if that
happens. We basically just want to see
continued downside. Generally I look at
structure as waves. This is something
interesting as well as to not get caught
up in every tiny little move that takes
place. Try to visualize structure as
larger waves. So average it out. That's
wave 1. That's wave two. That's wave
three. That's wave four. This is wave
five. We generally want to see some form
of meaningful retracement in order to
validate this wave of structure and give
us what we want to go lower. Okay. So
that's the idea of just averaging out
the waves of structure so that you can,
you know, see them for the full picture.
So now that the market's flattened out
quite a lot, I'd be interested in seeing
this structural low break. We could
validate this as a previous structural
high if we were to get some solid
closures. So there we have a closure. We
could go ahead and trail the stop loss
down quite aggressively behind price. So
now we'd see this as our next structure
wave. This is the following one from
there. This is where we're actually
starting to turn this trade into quite a
large one. In the worst case scenario
now we're probably going to get around
2%. Yeah, about 2% if the trade hits
stop. But if it continues with the
downward trend, we obviously have
potential to take this into the full
target. So allowing this to run forward
a little bit more. We see the market
come up. We are looking for a new low.
There's our new low. So let's just run
through price. Remove these off just to
keep it neat. We have the first break of
structure that we covered which is going
to be this one here. So we created a low
and we broke it which allowed us to
bring our stop to here. Then here we
created a new low. We broke it here
which allowed us to bring our stop down
to this point. Then we created this high
followed by this low which allowed us to
bring our stop to where it currently is.
And now once again we have created a new
breakin structure. So neaten that one
up. We've now pushed through this
30-inut low with a nice candle closure.
So we can bring our stop down to above
this high. We're now probably looking
close to 2.5 to 3% return in a worst
case scenario. And of course we can keep
running this towards the large target.
Let's run it forward a little bit more
with our trail stop. We are hoping that
the market will create a new validated
low lower than the previous one so we
don't get stopped out to keep that trend
intact. Okay, so ideally from here we
would see the market start to flip down.
We would need to see closures just like
that to validate the next low. Okay, now
this isn't always going to be so smooth
and this is why trading is a viable
thing to do and a very valuable thing to
do at that. In this instance, we have
had a reasonably nice trending market,
but markets aren't always going to go
the way you want them to. This one could
still flip on us rather aggressively and
that will sometimes happen. That is the
whole reason that we do this trading
method because if the market decides to
make a sharp reversal against us, at
least we are taking a good profit rather
than getting stopped out for zero. So,
what we can do now is put our stop loss
above this high and then providing the
market doesn't make a new high and
continues with the trending structure,
we should be just fine. Now, there's
also another method of trailing that we
can discuss in just one moment around
here. Sometimes you're going to be
getting very close to your target. So,
our total target for this simulated
trade is
7.7%. We're now at 6.3%.
This means we have dynamic riskreward to
consider. If the market gets all the way
back up here, we'll be closing this
trade for
2.6%. That means we're going to be
risking close to 4%. Okay,
3.7%ish just to hold this trade out for
around 1% more profit. So, we have a
dynamic riskreward problem where we're
basically going to be risking 3% to make
one. Now this is the only point of which
if you wanted to at this point we could
accept look this is a very big trade
we've closed 6.4%. We can start to work
with aggressive trading. So remember at
the start of the video I said generally
we don't want to just chase price down
with the stop. It's a point like this
where the dynamic riskreward is worth
considering that you may want to do
that. Now there is also nothing wrong
with leaving your stop loss where it is
here. You could leave this and just let
it run. Hopefully, it hits the target
and if it flips on you, then you're
still going to be taken out for around
2.6%. But if you are a bit more of a
riskaverse trader and you are seeing
that look, we've got a 6.3% return here.
I would rather lock in as much of this
as possible, you could do aggressive
trading, which is essentially where you
follow the individual candles down. So,
if we moved our stop loss to this level,
for example, that would mean worst case
on this trade now is going to be a 5.9%
return or pretty much a 6% return. You
could also, if you wanted to give it a
bit more leeway, put it above the
previous structural high. So, this would
be our standard position to put it in.
That's going to lock in a 4.6. Or if you
wanted to trail aggressively, you could
really follow price down and basically
on the formation of every new candle,
you would essentially then just follow
price through the range. Okay. Now, in
this instance, because of the
difference, this is already a 4.6
position. I would say just trading over
the previous structural high. It's
probably going to be the best move here.
And if we get a closure down here, then
I'm going to get seriously aggressive
with trailing the price. But providing
the market stays under this high, we
should be okay. And because we've now
managed to extend the profit potential
of this trade out to a minimum of 4.6,
I'd be happy to give this little bit of
leeway. If we miss out on this 1 and
a.5% return, that's fine. We're still
closing in 4.6. And if we run straight
down, perfect. We can aggressively trail
behind price and bring things down to
the takerit. Okay, so let's see how the
market goes. We see a small high being
created. Ideally, we would see a push
down and closure under the low. that
would then validate new lows and we
could get really aggressive with the
stop trailing. Now, in this instance, of
course, if the market reverses on us, we
are not hurt here. We've taken 4.6% from
a trade. So, we're happy either way. Of
course, the ideal scenario would be the
rundown, but we will just see which way
this goes from here. So, now that we've
started to push down, realistically, we
would then ideally want to start
aggressively trading. This is a weekend
gap. So this is just an anomaly.
Sometimes that's going to happen where
you get gaps up. For this trade, we have
then been taken out for a 4.6% return.
Realistically, we wouldn't be holding
this trade over the weekend this close
to the target. So it's more likely you'd
have taken around 5.5% by closing it
before the weekend started. But in a
simulation setting, of course, it's easy
to miss these little things. So let's
take a look at this trade. Then pull
this all the way across. We were stopped
out just here. This creates a 4.63%
return for us. If we take a look at the
profits on a $100,000 account, this is a
$14,681 balance. So that's a
$4,681 profit on that position. Now, if
the market was to reverse all the way on
us at any point throughout this journey,
we've basically built a scenario for
ourselves where we are getting out for a
win. Okay? By the time we got to here,
we were already break even. So just this
first push removed all risk from the
trade. By the time we got to here, we
had a minimum of around half percent
profit locked in. By the time we created
this high, we were going to be looking
at around 2% profit at a bare minimum.
And we've actually managed to follow
this all the way down successfully. But
had the market flipped on us at any
point, we'd have been out for a winning
position. So we've created a scenario
where it is purely winwin. Now we've
been stopped out down here due to a
market gap. Your more realistic close
for a position is going to be around
there, end of week, close the trade up
and let it go, which would be 5.87, but
even 4.6 is definitely something to be
rather happy with as well. And that's a
solid explanation of stop-loss trading,
which is an excellent way to minimize
losses and maximize returns from your
trades. Stop-loss trading helps to
minimize the risk of losing, helps to
lock in profits and creates win-win
scenarios, which is quite a rare thing
to get in trading. The simple process to
follow that I've outlined for you in
this video is once you've entered and
your stop loss is under a low or above a
high, you would then wait for validation
of a new high to form within the
existing trend, which requires a break
of structure. That low being validated
by the creation of a new high will then
allow you to move your stop loss up to
follow the structure. And again, the
formation of a new high will validate
the low and then you can move your stop
loss up to follow the structure. And the
cycle repeats like this until your
target is hit or the market reverses on
you, but you still get out with a nice
win. Now, if you want to build this into
a trading system, I have a free course
that you can enroll in right now. It's
going to take you through the process of
building trading systems, simplifying
your trading, improving the trades that
you take, and ultimately it's going to
help you to find success. So, if you
want to sign up to that, there is a link
at the top of the video description. And
if you don't want to do that, check out
this video next, which goes deeper into
the concepts of market structure and
trading with the trend. Thank you for
watching. I see you in the next